Bradford family papers, 1831-1941 C331
Indiana University Archives
Bradford family papers
1831-1941
1880-1935
Indiana University Archives
Bradford Family
C331
1.2 cubic feet 2 boxes
Joseph Bradford began acquiring land in Martinsville, Indiana, in the mid-1800s. The Bradford Sand Mining Company was founded by Joseph's son, Perry Bradford, in 1877 in Morgan County, Indiana. The family business was passed on to Albert and John Bradford in the early 1900s. It remained in the family until 1938 when John Bradford deeded 900 acres of the Bradford property to Indiana University. This property is currently known as the Bradford Woods. The Bradford family papers span 1831-1941 and consist of various financial and business records related to their property, as well as documentation of family history and family correspondence. The correspondence primarily dates from 1898 and consists largely of letters written to the Bradfords by Eliza (Bradford) and husband Dr. Grant Monical from Camp George in Georgia and later Cuba where Grant was a Captain in the Spanish-American War.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research. Advance notice is required.
Biographical Note
Joseph Bradford was born in 1815 in Maine, the son of Isaac and Shuah Jordan Bradford. His family later moved to Ohio. Joseph married Martha McMillian, and they moved to Indiana in 1854. The couple had five children: Perry (1859-1921), Eliza (1860-1933), Clara (1862-1940), John (1864-1941), and Albert (1868-1936). Perry, John, and Albert lived on the family farm their entire lives and operated the Bradford Sand Mining Company. They were also prominent landowners and active in their community. Eliza married Grant Monical, a doctor. Grant served during the Spanish-American War. He spent most of his career practicing medicine in Morgan County, Indiana. Clara married George L. Bush. The couple lived in Riverside, California and had two children, Bernard and Selma. The Bradford family were descendants of Governor William Bradford who came to America in the Mayflower.
In the mid-1800s, Joseph Bradford and his brother-in-law, Joseph Campbell, began acquiring land in Martinsville, Indiana. In 1855, Joseph and Martha Bradford moved to what is today known as Bradford Woods. Their sons Perry, John, and Albert later discovered valuable sand on the property. In 1877, Perry Bradford successfully submitted the Bradford Sand Mining Company's articles of association to the Morgan County chamber of commerce, and the family began mining the sand and selling it to foundries. Over the years, the business grew, and additional land was acquired through the 1920s. Although the financial records of the company suggest they found themselves in some debt, the Bradfords and the Bradford Sand Mining Company survived the 1929 stock market crash. After Albert's death in 1936, all of the family's land and stock were transferred to John.
In 1938, John Bradford deeded 900 acres of the Bradford family land to Indiana University for the use of the Riley Hospital for Children. This area, now known as the Bradford Woods, was first developed by Dr. Reynold Carlson and the Indiana University Recreation Department. Under the direction of Dr. Carlson, the Bradford Woods became a day camp area for handicapped children from Riley Hospital. Today Bradford Woods provides experiential and therapeutic outdoor programs for both adults and children.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series, the Bradford Sand Mining Company and the Bradford family. The former is further arranged into two Subseries: Business documentation and Land development. The Bradford Family series is arranged into six Subseries: Correspondence, Family history, Finances, Land deeds, Local memorabilia, and Wills.
Scope and Content Note
The Bradford family collection contains records documenting the Bradford Sand Mining Company as well as papers pertaining to the Bradford family.
Spanning the period from 1831 to 1941, materials in the Bradford Sand Mining Company series include various items documenting the business activities related to land development by the company. Further organized into two subseries, the Business documentation subseries include the articles of association from 1877; advertising brochures from circa 1888; correspondence with Garden City Sand Company, The Peerless Sand Company, and the Hoosier Moulding Sand Company; and financial records such as checkbook stubs and rough dock inventories. The bulk of the material in the Bradford Sand Mining Company series relates to land development. Within this subseries are records dealing with electric service, land acquisition, pipelines, and roadway construction. Common items in all four topic areas are petitions to build and right-of-way grants. Items specific to electric service include pole agreements and a bill of sale for electrical wires. Materials relating to pipelines also include a sketch mapping out where the pipelines are located. Land acquisition materials consist primarily of land grant agreements. Among the items relating to roadway construction is an 1876 observer's journal documenting progress made up to that point.
The second series contains papers pertaining to the Bradford family from 1865 to 1940. This series is further organized into six subseries: Correspondence, Family history, Finances, Land deeds and grants, Local memorabilia, and Wills. Correspondence consists largely of letters written to the Bradfords by Eliza (Bradford) and husband Dr. Grant Monical from Camp George in Georgia and later Cuba where Grant was a Captain in the Spanish-American War. Documenting the Bradford family history is an undated pencil sketch of the family tree accompanied by a related piece of correspondence. There are also requests from Horace Standish Bradford and the Society of Mayflower Descendants for further genealogical information. Financial items include checkbook stubs from the early 1900s, account balance sheets, and state income tax forms spanning from the period from 1925 to 1940. A large collection of land deeds documenting the passing of family land from one generation to the next covers 68 years, from 1865 to 1933. The Memorabilia subseries includes an undated Republican Party election flyer, Perry Bradford's certificate from Indianapolis Business College indicating he paid for Life Membership, which allowed him to take courses for life, a 1930 Morgan County Farmer's Yearbook, and what appears to be a prose book, handwritten, author unknown. Also held in the Bradford family collection are the wills of Albert and Perry Bradford, various members of the Bradford family, Joseph Campbell, and John H. Rothrock, Sr.
Separated Material
Five land grant certificates (1831-1851) are stored with oversized materials, and one plot plan on blueprint was removed and stored with the Archives' architectural records. Please consult staff for more details.
Acquisition Information
Accession Information: 0461 and 7582
Sand and gravel mines and mining --Indiana --Archives.; Spanish-American War, 1898 --History --Sources.; Soldiers --Indiana --Correspondence.; Morgan County (Ind.) --History --Sources.; Bradford Woods Outdoor Education Center (Indiana University, Bloomington) -- History -- Sources; Bradford Sand Mining Company; Bradford Family -- Archives; Bradford Family -- Correspondence; Bradford Sand Mining Company -- Archives; Bradford Sand Mining Company -- Records and correspondence; Bradford Sand Mining Company -- History -- Sources
- Bradford Sand Mining Company, 1847-1941; undated (Box 1)
  - Business documentation, 1877-1941; undated (Box 1)
    - Advertising materials, circa 1888, undated (Box 1)
    - Articles of Association, transfer of ownership, 1877; 1925 (Box 1)
    - Business correspondence, 1926; 1937 (Box 1)
    - Finances, 1923-1941; undated (Box 1)
    - Rough inventories, undated (Box 1)
  - Land development, 1847-1939 (Box 1)
    - Electric service, 1907-1925 (Box 1)
    - Land acquisition, 1847-1937 (Box 1)
    - Pipeline, 1908-1939 (Box 1)
    - Roadway construction, 1876-1937 (Box 1)
- Bradford family, 1831-1940; undated (Box 1)
  - Correspondence, 1898-1926 (Box 1)
    - Perry Bradford, 1898-1910 (Box 1)
    - A.A. Humphrey, 1926 (Box 1)
    - Eliza Monical, 1898 (Box 1)
    - Grant Monical, 1898 (Box 1)
      General
      (Last letter is missing first page.)
  - Family history, 1874-1914 (Box 1)
    - Martha Bradford's certificate appointing her guardian for Joseph Bradford's children, 1874 (Box 1)
    - Horace Standish Bradford, 1898; 1904 (Box 1)
      (Request for information and announcement of Bradford family histories)
    - Society of Mayflower Descendants, 1914 (Box 1)
      (Includes family tree)
  - Finances, 1880-1940; undated (Box 1)
    - Finances, 1880-1938; undated (Box 1)
    - State income tax (Box 1)
      - 1925-1929 (Box 1)
      - 1930-1934 (Box 1)
      - 1935-1940 (Box 1)
  - Land deeds and grants, 1831-1937 (Box 2)
    - Bradford brothers' land agreement, 1917 (Box 2)
    - Bradford Orchards property lease, 1937 (Box 2)
    - Land grants (Box 2)
      (oversized)
      - 1831-1851 (Box 2)
      - 1865-1893 (Box 2)
      - 1894-1899 (Box 2)
      - 1901-1907 (Box 2)
      - 1908-1910 (Box 2)
      - 1911-1933 (Box 2)
  - Memorabilia, 1877; 1930; undated (Box 2)
    - Perry Bradford's certificate from Indianapolis Business College, 1877 (Box 2)
    - Morgan County Farmer's Yearbook, 1930 (Box 2)
    - Prose Book, undated (Box 2)
      (handwritten, unknown author)
    - Republican Party flyer, undated (Box 2)
  - Wills, 1873-1940 (Box 2)
    - Albert Bradford, 1899; 1937 (Box 2)
    - John Bradford, 1940 (Box 2)
    - John W. Bradford, 1899 (Box 2)
    - Joseph Bradford, 1873 (Box 2)
    - Martha E. Bradford, 1892 (Box 2)
    - Perry Bradford, 1921-1938 (Box 2)
    - Joseph Campbell, 1899 (Box 2)
    - John H. Rothrock, Sr., 1917 (Box 2)